Guide to the Paul and Charlotte Reynolds Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Paul and Charlotte Reynolds Papers
1909-2004
RG 193
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(8 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, collected material, and photographs document the lives and work of Paul R. and Charlotte Reynolds. The Reynolds were missionaries in north China, serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions (1921-1936).
Reynolds, Paul Russell
Reynolds, Charlotte Belknap
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert Reynolds, 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1891 Jan 15 Paul R. Reynolds born in Bushnell, IL, son of Othello and Catherine Caldwell Reynolds
1918 Following education at Wabash College and Ellsworth College, received B.D. from Chicago Theological Seminary
1918-1920 In YMCA work during World War I and then in the chaplaincy. Spent two years as secretary of Congregational Education Society.
1921 May 30 Married Charlotte Belknap of Oak Park, graduate of Oberlin College, a social worker.
1921 May 30 Paul and Charlotte ommissioned as missionaries, serving under American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions (ABCFM); supported by Winnetka Congregational Church
1921 Oct 13 Went to China
1922-1927 After a year in Language School in Peking, the Reynolds were stationed in Fenchow, Shansi Province in Northwest China. Work was in the field of religious education, involving teaching and supervision of work over a large area in Shansi and Shensi provinces.
1927-1928 Studied at Union Seminary and Columbia University; awarded M.A. Received D.D. from Chicago Theological Seminary.
1928-1935 Back in China; Chairman of North China Council Committee on Religious Education, representative of the North China Congregational churches on the National Committee of Religious Education.
1936-1953 While home on furlough and studying at Berea, KY, Paul wasmade field secretary of Divinity of Christian Education of the Congregational churches. Paul and Charlotte served as secretaries for the Young Adult and Family Life program.
1954-1957 Served as pastor of Pleasant Hill Community Church, Pleasant Hill, TN and direcotr of Community Center
1957/8 Suffered heart attack and was forced to resign positions in Pleasant Hill.
1960- Paul and Charlotte members of Board of Directors of Southeast Convention of Congregational churches, Board of Trustees of Southern Union College.
1974 Oct Paul died.
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence
II. Writings and Notes
III. Collected Material
IV. Biographical Documentation
V. Photographs and Slides
This collection provides valuable detailed information about the work of missionaries in the North China Mission of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. It complements other missionary papers available at the Yale Divinity Library, including those of Harold Matthews, Winfield McLean, Percy Watson, Ernest and Olivia Ikenberry, Earle and Thelma Ballou, and the Bright family.
Series I, Correspondence, includes letters written by the Reynolds to and from their family members in the United States as well as letters to and from missionary colleagues and friends, and circular letters.
Series II, Writings and Notes, contains articles and papers by Paul and Charlotte as well as writings of others. A series of letters written by Paul for publication in the Winnetka Weekly Talk in 1924 provide vivid and detailed descriptions of his activities in China. There are also notes and talks prepared by Paul and Charlotte relating to Fenchow and other areas where they visited, Chinese customs, as well as reports on events and meetings.
Series III, Collected Material, is largely related to the ABCFM North China mission, providing "on the ground" information about schools, buildings, conferences, etc. There is a fairly complete run of the mission publication "Fenchow" from the years when the Reynolds were in China, 1922-1936.
Series IV, Biographical Documentation, includes personal documents, autobiographical statements, and clippings. Of particular note is the extensive compilation, "Charlotte and Paul Reynolds - a Chronicle", which was prepared by Jo Reynolds, wife of the Reynolds' son Robert, in 1988. This privately published volume includes excerpts from the journal of Charlotte, excerpts from letters and talks, and editorial comment providing the context for the primary source documents.
The Photographs and Slides of Series V are well identified and provide a glimpse into the everyday life of the missionaries and the schools and hospitals with which they were involved. In addition to loose photographs, there are seven albums of photographs with extensive captions. The final box of this collection contains glass lantern slides of buildings, scenes, transportation, and people in China. These slides were used by the Reynolds when they visited churches in the U.S. to talk about their work in China.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings and Notes
III. Collected Material
IV. Biographical Documentation
V. Photographs and Slides
Missions -- China; Missionaries; Reynolds, Charlotte Belknap; Reynolds, Paul Russell; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
- I. Correspondence, Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - Charlotte (CBR) and Paul (PRR) to/from parents in U.S., 1922-1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - CBR and PRR to/from parents in U.S., 1928-1930 Sep (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - CBR and PRR to/from parents in U.S., 1930 Oct - 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - CBR to/from PRR, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - PRR and CBR to their children, 1950s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bob (son) to PRR and CBR (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - CBR and CRR to/from extended family, 1909-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General correspondence
    - Circular letters of the Reynolds, 1924-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - CBR to/from others, incl. Hern, Hemingways, 1926-1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - CBR to/from others, incl. "Mother Marie", Pye, 1936-1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and friends: Adams - Ballou, 1921-1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Barbour - Blair, 1922-1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Boynton - Burton, 1922-1931 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Carlson - Cushman, 1922-1948 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Jim Davies, 1921-1934 (Box 1, Folder 15-19)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Danforth - Grimes, 1921-1935 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Robert Gammon, 1921-1935 (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Haswell - Luan, 1921-1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Marsh - McDermott, 1921-1935 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: McKinney - Myers, 1921-1936 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Nebraska Y.P. - Reimer, 1921-1947 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Richards - Seabury, 1920-1935 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Sheldon - Williams, 1921-1936 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: Winnetka Church, 1921-1936 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Letters to/from colleagues and supporters: first names and fragments, 1922-1936 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence of others
    - Letters of others, B - W (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Letters of others, first names and unidentified (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Circular letters of missionary colleagues: B-M (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
    - Circular letters of missionary colleagues: N - Y (Box 3, Folder 37-38)
- Writings and Notes, Series II
  - Writings of PRR
    - Incl. letters published in Winnetka Weekly Talk: "Reynolds Party Reaches Shensi Where Opium Industry Thrives", "Blinding Sand Storm Envelops Winnetka Missionary's Party", "Reynolds Relates Two Thrillers Concerning Bandits' Operations" (1924); Report on Annual Meeting of the Promotional Board of the North China Mission, Lintsing, Shantung (1930); article in Chinese Recorder: "Religion and Revolution" (1934); poems, 1924-1934 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Incl. "Record of a world trip", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Incl "Trip to Pingyang and thru the mountains" and report re. Fenchow (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Writings of CBR
    - Incl. "The Family in China", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Incl. notes on Fenchow, Temples, Chinese Festivals, Dramatics, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Notes and writings re. China (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Writings of others
    - Incl. "A Desperate Struggle" - essay re. communism in China, re. the "Yu Tao Ho Summer Conference Meeting in Shansi Province, North China for preachers, teachers, bible women and hospital assistants" - writings by Ethel Davis, Gertrude Kellogg, Rev. Han, Erwin Hertz, and others (Box 3, Folder 46)
- III. Collected Material, Series III
  - Related to North China Mission (ABCFM)
    - Obituaries (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Mission schools and students (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Mission buildings, etc. (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Evangelism reports (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Conference reports, minutes, misc. (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Chinese language material (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Fenchow - publication of the Fenchow Station, ABCFM, 1922-1936 (Box 4, Folder 53-57)
    - China newsletters, 1947-1963 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Re. China in general
    - Newsclippings, 1922-1950 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Personal items and memorabilia
    - Programs from events (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Meetings and conferences (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Cards and collected poems (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Tributes to and reminiscences of Charlotte's mother (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Biblical scrapbook by children (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Miscellaneous items (Box 4, Folder 65)
- IV. Biographical Documentation, Series IV
  - Personal histories, ordination, commissioning to China, other services, obituary (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Documents - military, wills, insurance, etc. (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Births and dedications of children; death of Happy (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Memoirs of Robert B. Reynolds, Sr., son of CBR and PRR, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Newsclippings re. Reynolds; misc. re. life in China, including scripts for Christmas plays, church services, 1929-1934 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - "Charlotte and Paul Reynolds - A Chronicle" compiled and edited by Jo Reynolds, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 72)
- V. Photographs and Slides, Series V
  - Photographs
    - Reynolds family, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - Missionary friends and others; hospital, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Mission schools and students, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Chinese families and groups, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Occupations, transportation, processions, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Church-related, buildings, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Album: Catherine S. Harwood Bible Training School, Fenchow, Shani: incl. photographs re. Woolwork Department, Agricultural Department, Department of Animal Husbandry, Nursery Department, Religous Education projects, Social Service projects, ca. 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Album: Fenchow - scenes from area, Fenchow Hospital, Harwood Hospital, Girls School, Anti-Opium Day, ca. 1924-1926 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Album: Fenchow, Book I: scenes from area - transportation, cave homes, Chinese groups, etc., ca. 1920s (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Album: Fenchow, Book II: scenes from area - village life, transportation, etc., ca. 1920s (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Small albums: Lydia Lord Davis Girls School, Fenchow YMCA, Ming I Memorial High School, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Album: travels, Chinese people, animals, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Groups - some with Reynolds, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 7, Folder 86-87)
    - Chinese family groups, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - Individual Chinese young men, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - School and assorted groups, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Chinese wedding and scenes, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Slides
    - Glass lantern slides - buildings, scenes, transportation, groups, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 8, Folder 62)